A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 25 - Office of Research and Innovation
  - RG 25/19 - Biocomplexity Institute of Virginia Tech [obsolete, April 2019; see RG 25/16]
    The Virginia Bioinformatics Institute was founded in 2000. In 2016, it became the Biocomplexity Institute of Virginia Tech. In 2019, the insitutute's resources transferred to the Fralin Life Sciences Institute [RG 25/16].
    May include MetroLab Network partnership; Interdisciplinary Ph.D. program in Genetics, Bioinformatics and Computational Biology (GBCB); Kids' Tech University; Nutritional Immunology and Molecular Medicine Laboratory (NIMML); Network Dynamics and Simulation Science Laboratory (NDSSL); Social and Decision Analytics Laboratory; Data Science for Public Good program (DSPG); STEM Summer Workshop; Genomics Sequencing Center
  - RG 25/20 - Virginia Tech Transportation Institute (VTTI)
    The Center for Transportation Research was renamed the Virginia Tech Transportation Institute (VTTI).
    May include Center for Technology Development; Center for Sustainable Mobility; Smart Road; Spin electric scooters; Interstate 81 Cooridor Coalition (I-81)
  - RG 25/21 - Virginia Tech Carilion Research Institute [obsolete; see RG 46]
  - RG 25/22 - Institute for Creativity, Arts, and Technology (ICAT)
    May include Virginia Science Festival; Maker Camp; ICAT Creativity and Innovation Day; Instrument Maker Camp; ACCelerate Creativity and Innovation Festival; Creativity and Innovation Strategic Growth Area; Moogfest
    See also RG 5/17.
  - RG 25/23 - University Research Centers
    May include Institute for Biomedical and Public Health Sciences
  - RG 25/24 - Virginia Tech Intellectual Properties
  - RG 25/25 - Office of Scholarly Integrity and Research Compliance [formerly Office of Research Compliance, until 2018]
    May include Institutional Review Board (IRB)
  - RG 25/26 - Virginia Tech Applied Research Corporation (VT-ARC)
  - RG 25/27 - Office of Research Education and Administrative Compliance
    May include Export and Secure Research Compliance; NIH K and New Investigator R01 Proposal Preparation Program
  - RG 25/28 - Ted and Karyn Hume Center for National Security and Technology
    May include Cybersecurity; Commonwealth Cyber Initiative
    See also RG 25/17; RG 50/4.
- Record Group 26 - Virginia Cooperative Extension (VCE)
  Extension work at the university can trace its roots to 1906 when an extension program was established in Virginia. When the Smith-Lever Act of 1914 was passed, overall authority for extension, or demonstration, work was transferred to Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VPI), with Virginia State College (later Virginia State University (VSU)) as a division initially serving Black communities. At that time, it became the Agricultural Extension, also called the Cooperative Extension Service.
  In 1966, the Virginia General Assembly established the VPI Extension Division, which combined the Cooperative Extension Service, General Extension Division, State Technical Services, and Continuing Education Center. In 1995, the Division became the Virginia Cooperative Extension and Agricultural Experiment Station Division, often shortened to the Virginia Cooperative Extension (VCE), operated jointly by VT and VSU.
  May include State Technical Services; Proposal Writing Institute; Horseman's Short Course; Virginia Master Naturalist program
  - RG 26 - Virginia Cooperative Extension (Information)
  - RG 26 - Virginia Cooperative Extension (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 26a - Administrative (Publications)
  - RG 26b - Job Announcements
  - RG 26c - Newsletters
  - RG 26d - Virginia Gardener
    May include Virginia Extension Service Association (VESA)
  - RG 26e - Seminars and Conferences
    May include Family Resources Conference; Virginia Farm to Table Conference; Virginia Agritourism Conference
    - RG 26e - Seminars and Conferences, through 1989
      May include Family Resources Conference; Virginia Farm to Table Conference
    - RG 26e - Seminars and Conferences, 1990-present (Publications)
  - RG 26f - Forms and Surveys [items also in Oversize Folder 1]
  - RG 26/1a - Bureau of Community Development [obsolete]
    The Bureau of Community Development was started in 1929. Its purpose was to assist cities and Chambers of Commerce in making industrial surveys and other studies for industrial development, as well as advising on municipal engineering projects and providing library services for municipal affairs. In 1937, the bureau ceased to exist, and its activities were continued by the Engineering Extension Division [RG 26/1] as a whole.
  - RG 26/2 - Agricultural Extension Service [obsolete]
    The Agricultural Extension began with the passage of the Smith-Lever Act in 1914, but can trace its roots back to 1906 when extension work in agriculture and home economics began in Virginia. In 1966, the Agricultural Extension Service merged into the Extension Division [RG 26] of Virginia Tech.
    - RG 26/2/1 - Master Gardeners [items in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 26/3 - Graduate Life Center at Donaldson Brown (GLC) [obsolete, 2019; see RG 35/4] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Division of Continuing Education was created in 1968 as part of the Virginia Cooperative Extension. It oversaw the Continuing Education Center (CEC), later renamed the Donaldson Brown Center for Continuing Education, the Donaldson Brown Hotel and Conference Center, and Graduate Life Center at Donaldson Brown (GLC). The Division moved to Outreach and International Affairs in 1990 and was renamed Continuing and Professional Education [RG 35/4].
    May include Donaldson Brown Hotel and Conference Center; Continuing Education Center; Administrator's Conferences; Continuing Education Unit (CEU)
    See also RG 6/3/2b; RG 8/2/1; RG 22; RG 35/4.
    - RG 26/3 - Graduate Life Center at Donaldson Brown (Information)
    - RG 26/3 - Graduate Life Center at Donaldson Brown (Publications)
    - RG 26/3/1 - Seminars, Conferences, etc. through 1989 (Publications)
    - RG 26/3/1 - Seminars, Conferences, etc., 1990-present (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 26/3/2 - Non-Credit Conference Listings, through 1989
    - RG 26/3/2 - Non-Credit Conference Listings, 1990-present
    - RG 26/3/3 - Dining and Entertainment (Publications)
  - RG 26/4 - 4-H, FFA (Future Farmers of America), FHA (Future Homemakers of America) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include W. E. Skelton 4-H Educational Conference Center at Smith Mountain Lake
    - RG 26/4/2 - Virginia 4-H Horse Program
  - RG 26/5 - Technical Resources
    May include Virginia State Technical Services Program
  - RG 26/6 - Community Resource Development
  - RG 26/7 - Institute for Leadership and Volunteer Development
    The Institute for Leadership and Volunteer Development was formerly Center for Volunteer Development.
    - RG 26/7 - Institute for Leadership and Volunteer Development (Information)
    - RG 26/7 - Institute for Leadership and Volunteer Development (Publications)
    - RG 26/7a - Reports, Monographs
    - RG 26/7b - Newsletter
  - RG 26/8 - Agri-Tech Week
    May include Animal Industry Day
  - RG 26/9 - Institute of Rural Affairs
- Record Group 27 - Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc.
  The VPI Educational Foundation was established by authority of the Board of Visitors in 1948 as a tax-exempt, non-profit corporation to "work toward increasing gifts and endowments made to the college." The Board of Directors for the Foundation composed of representatives from the administration, Board of Visitors [RG 1], Alumni Association [RG 29], and business leaders from inside and outside the state. In 1983, the Foundation's name was changed to the Virginia Tech Educational Foundation, Inc. In 1985, the Executive Council of the Foundation took on the responsibilities of the Development Council [RG 28].
  May include VTC Innovation Fund / VTC Seed Fund; Dean Andy Swiger Land-Grant Award Endowment; Virginia Tech endowment; Child care center partnerships
  - RG 27 - Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc. (Information)
  - RG 27 - Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc. (Publications)
  - RG 27/1 - WVTF
    The Virginia Western Community College (VWCC) in Roanoke, Virginia, started WVWR-FM in 1973. VWCC sold the station to the Virginia Tech Foundation, Inc., in 1981, and the station became WVTF in April or May 1982.
    May include Radio IQ; The Producers Circle
  - RG 27/2 - Corporate Research Center (CRC)
    A study commissioned by the Virginia Tech Foundation in 1985 recommended that the Foundation establish a "wholly owned subsidiary corporation to develop and operate" a corporate research center. In response to the study, the foundation established the Virginia Tech Corporate Research Center, Inc., which began operation on June 13, 1985.
    May include University Research Park; Tech Center Research Park in Newport News; Virginia Tech Faculty Entrepreneur Hall of Fame
  - RG 27/3 - VT KnowledgeWorks
    May include Global Entrepreneurship Challenge [obsolete; see RG 16/13]
- Record Group 28 - Development Council [obsolete, 1985; see RG 27]
  The Development Council was established in 1964 to "provide overall coordination" of the University's development program. The Council was composed of the executive committees of the Board of Visitors [RG 1/3], Alumni Association [RG 29], and VPI Education Foundation [RG 27], as well as the president of the Virginia Tech Student Aid Association [RG 10/6]. The Council was replaced by the Executive Council of the Virginia Tech Educational Foundation, Inc. [RG 27] in 1985.
- Record Group 29 - Alumni Association
  On August 11, 1875, Virginia Tech's first Alumni Association was formed by the twelve members of the first graduating class. In 1891, the Association was reorganized, under a new constitution, and began publishing an Alumni Register. The Association was incorporated on June 23, 1924. In 1964, new bylaws were adopted and the Association became more closely linked with the University. At the same time, the title of Alumni Secretary was changed to Director of Alumni Affairs, then to Executive Director in 1972, and then to Executive Vice-President in 1980. In 1990, the Alumni Association became an official part of the University, associated with the Office of Alumni Relations. The Office for Alumni Relations merged with the offices of University Development and University Relations into the Advancement Division [RG 21] in July 2015.
  May include Homecoming Day; Dix Plan for Class Reunion; Monteith Award; University Distinguished Professors; Women's Weekend; Grad Fair
  See also RG 21.
  - RG 29 - Alumni Association (Information)
  - RG 29 - Alumni Association (Publications)
  - RG 29a - New River Chapter
  - RG 29b - Funds
  - RG 29c - Directories
  - RG 29/1 - Memorial Committees
    - RG 29/1/1 - Memorial Awards
  - RG 29/2 - Women's Chapter [obsolete, 1971]
    A VPI Alumnae Society was organized in 1933 for women graduates. This Society became the Women's Chapter of the VPI Alumni Association in 1955, but was dissolved in 1971.
  - RG 29/3 - Faculty Awards [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Academy of Teaching Excellence; Committee for Excellence in Teaching [see also RG 2/11]; University Distinguished Professors; Wine Faculty Achievement Award; Sporn Awards
    See also RG 29/9.
  - RG 29/4 - University Club
    A Virginia Tech faculty group organized the University Club in 1925. Soon the club gained 125 members and has continued to grow throughout the years. The clubhouse, formerly located on Otey Street, was built in June 1929 on land leased from the university. The Virginia Tech Foundation purchased the clubhouse in 2019 and tore it down the next year.
  - RG 29/5 - Old Guard - Society of the Golden Alumni
    In 1967, the Alumni Association formed the Old Guard for alumni who graduated 50 years or more previously. In Fall of 2017, the Old Guard changed its name to the Old Guard - Society of the Golden Alumni, to encourage membership among civilian alumni (i.e. alumni who did not participate in the Corps of Cadets). Each class is inducted into the Old Guard during Homecoming [RG 29/6].
    May include 50th Reunions
    See also RG 29/6; RG 31/13/5.
  - RG 29/6 - Homecoming
  - RG 29/7 - Civil War Weekend
    See also RG 21/8.
  - RG 29/8 - Black Alumni
    See also RG 29/9 for Influential Black Alumni Awards.
  - RG 29/9 - Alumni Awards
    May include University Distinguished Achievement Award; Alumni Distinguished Service Awards; Alumni Awards for Excellence; Influential Black Alumni Awards
  - RG 29/10 - Ex Lapide Society
    May include LGBTQ+ alumni; Out at Work Student and Alumni Networking
  - RG 29/11 - Reunion Weekend
    The Alumni Association initiated its first reunion weekend in 2018. Prior to this, classes were invited on specific weekends. Prior reunions were held throughout the fall for classes celebrating milestone anniversaries.
- Record Group 30 - Faculty Organizations
  See also RG 6 for other staff- and employee-related organizations; RG 31 for student-related organizations.
  - RG 30 - Faculty Organizations (Information)
  - RG 30 - Faculty Organizations (Publications)
  - RG 30/1 - Faculty Meetings
    From the early years of the institution until the formation of a formal senate [RG 30/3] in 1969, meetings of the general faculty were held on a regular basis to discuss policies, procedures, and issues concerning the university.
    See also RG 30/3.
  - RG 30/2 - Science Council [obsolete, 1960]
    The VPI Science Club was organized in 1914 by "those interested in scientific work" at the university. The club was primarily a faculty organization, but was open to undergraduate students in the "Junior or Senior classes." In 1958, the Science Club changed its name to the VPI Science Council, developed new objectives, and altered its organizational structure, "to better the promotion of science." At that time, it became wholly a faculty organization, "with particular emphasis given to coordinating science activities where needed, formulating resolutions, and sponsoring special council projects." The organization was abolished in 1960.
    May include Virginia Academy and Junior Academy of Sciences Meetings on Campus
  - RG 30/3 - Faculty Senate [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Faculty Senate was formed in 1969 by approval of the Board of Visitors to "articulate faculty views on campus policies and procedures." Prior to their formation, general faculty held meetings on a regular basis [RG 30/1].
    May include Student Perceptions of Teaching (SPOT) [see also RG 9/1]
    See also RG 5/19; RG 9/1; RG 30/1.
  - RG 30/4 - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), Virginia Tech Chapter
    The American Association of University Professors (AAUP) is a national organization of university professors, with state and local chapters, concerned with all aspects of teaching in higher education. It was formed in 1915.
    May include Association of American Colleges and Universities
  - RG 30/5 - Virginia Tech Women's Club
    Founded in 1965, the Faculty Women's Club became the Virginia Tech Women's Club (VTWC) in 2017.
  - RG 30/5a - American Association of University Women (AAUW), Virginia Tech Chapter
    The American Association of University Women (AAUW) began in 1881. The Virginia Tech chapter was formed in 1926.
  - RG 30/6 - Black Faculty/Staff Caucus
  - RG 30/7 - Women's Network
    May include Women's Communication Network Group
    - RG 30/7 - Women's Network (Information)
    - RG 30/7 - Women's Network (Publications)
  - RG 30/8 - Sigma Xi: The Scientific Research Honor Society
    The Virginia Tech Chapter of Sigma Xi: The Scientific Research Honor Society was granted its charter by the national society in 1940.
  - RG 30/9 - Organization of Women Faculty
  - RG 30/10 - Faculty/Staff Awards [items also in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 30/11 - LGBT Caucus
    Formed in 1992, the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Caucus at Virginia Tech (LGBT Caucus) out of the Women's Network as the LGB Caucus. Transgender was added to the name and gender identity to the group's mission statement in 2002. The Caucus is open to students, staff, faculty, and the public.
    May include Lavender Ceremony; Gay in Appalachia; Lambda Horizon Scholarship
    See also RG 8/16; RG 31/14/1.
  - RG 30/12 - Disability Alliance and Caucus
    Formed in 2015, the Disability Alliance and Caucus is open to all community members and allies. The Caucus is specifically for employees of Virginia Tech.
- Record Group 31 - Student Organizations and Publications
  The first student organization at Virginia Tech was the Virginia Literary Society, formed in 1872, which was the forerunner of both the Lee and Maury Literary Societies. The Lee and Maury Literary Societies were responsible for the first student publication, the Gray Jacket, which was published sporadically between 1875 and 1906. Since those early days, there have been many student organizations and student publications, of various types.
  May include Maury Literary Society; National Residence Hall Honorary; Psi Chi (psychology); Virginia Tech Odysseey of the Mind
  - RG 31 - Student Organizations (Information)
  - RG 31 - Student Organizations (Publications)
  - RG 31/1 - City, County, and Sectional Clubs
    - RG 31/1/1 - Apple Club
    - RG 31/1/2 - Baltimore Polytechnic Institute Alumni Club
    - RG 31/1/3 - Black Diamond Club
    - RG 31/1/4 - Brush Mountain Academy
    - RG 31/1/5 - Cosmopolitan Club [obsolete; see RG 31/6/6]
    - RG 31/1/6 - Eastern Shore Anchor Club
    - RG 31/1/7 - Lonesome Pine Club
    - RG 31/1/8 - Lynchburg Club
    - RG 31/1/9 - Northern Neck Club
    - RG 31/1/10 - Peanut Club
    - RG 31/1/11 - Roanoke Club
    - RG 31/1/12 - Shenandoah Valley Club
  - RG 31/2 - Curricular Clubs (Student/Professional Groups)
    May include Accounting Society [see also RG 31/2/22]; Administrative Management Society; All-American Dairy Show; Alpha Tau Alpha (Vocational Agriculture); American Congress on Surveying and Mapping; American Fisheries Society; American Institute of Chemical Engineers; American Society for [of] Metals; American Society for Personnel Administration; American Society of Interior Designers; Biochemistry Club; Biomedical Engineering Society; Biology Club; Building Women in Construction; Business Club [obsolete]; Commodity Investing by Students (COINS); Computer Club; Conservation and Recreation Society; D.E.U.S. (Urban and Regional Studies); English Club; Entomological Society; Executive Forum (Business); Fashion Merchandising and Design Society; Forest Products Research Society; Geography Club [charter revoked 1975]; Graduate Women in Business; Health Physics Society; Holden Society [obsolete; see RG 31/2/34]]; Hyperloop of Virginia Tech / Vhyper; International Food Service Executives Association; Manchester League; Operations Research Society of America; Parapsychology Club; Plant Protection Club; Political Economy Union; Political Science Club; Pre-Law Society; Pre-Veterinary Club; Professional Health, Physical Education, and Recreation Association; Professional Recreation Association; Psychology Club; Public Relations Student Society of America; The Ridge Runner; Russian Club; Society of American Foresters; Society of American Military Engineers; Society of Engineering Science; Society of Professional Journalists; Sociology Club; Statistics Club; Student Alliance for Landscaping Architecture; Student Music Educators Conference; Triangle Fraternity (architecture) [see also RG 9/3, 1/24/1975]; Urban Affairs Exchange; Vocational Industrial Club; VT Hacks / Hackathon; Institute of Traffic Engineers; Society for Collegiate Journalists; Computational Modeling and Data Analytics Club / DataFest; Pamplin Reinventing Social Media (PRISM, Pamplin College of Business student-run ad agency); Alpha Omega Alpha (medical honor society); Entrepreneur Club at Virginia Tech; Alpha Chi Sigma (chemistry society); Engineers Without Borders; American Veterinary Medical Association; Phil Alpha Delta [Pre-law]; Glossolalia literary festival; GitHub student group; Instructional Technology Student Association; Student American Veterinary Medical Association; American Foundry Society; Consulting Group at Virginia Tech; Black Students in STEM (BSS)
    - RG 31/2/1 - Astronomy Club
    - RG 31/2/2 - Agricultural Economics Club
    - RG 31/2/3 - Agricultural Club Council
      May include Agronomy Club; Agronomy Society of America; Agronomy Economics Club
      See also RG 31/2/6.
    - RG 31/2/4 - Agricultural Education Society
    - RG 31/2/5 - Agricultural Technology Club
    - RG 31/2/6 - Agronomy Club
      See also RG 31/2/3.
    - RG 31/2/7 - Alpha Epsilon Rho (Broadcasting)
    - RG 31/2/8 - Alpha Rho Chi (Architecture)
    - RG 31/2/9 - American Association of Textile Chemists and Colorists
    - RG 31/2/10 - American Chemical Association / American Chemical Society
    - RG 31/2/11 - American Institute of Aeronautics & Astronautics
    - RG 31/2/12 - American Institute of Architects
    - RG 31/2/13 - American Institute of Industrial Engineers
    - RG 31/2/14 - American Marketing Association
    - RG 31/2/15 - American Nuclear Society
    - RG 31/2/16 - American Society of Agricultural Engineers
    - RG 31/2/17 - American Society of Civil Engineers
    - RG 31/2/18 - American Society of Landscape Architects
    - RG 31/2/19 - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME)
    - RG 31/2/20 - Association for the Advancement of Engineering / Association for the Advancement of Engineers
    - RG 31/2/21 - Association for Computing Machinery
    - RG 31/2/22 - Beta Alpha Psi (Accounting)
    - RG 31/2/24 - Burkhart Mining Society
    - RG 31/2/25 - Dairy Science Club
      May include American Dairy Science Association; All-American Dairy Show; Dairy Club
      - RG 31/2/25a - Dairy Day
    - RG 31/2/26 - Delta Pi Epsilon (Business Administration/Business Education)
    - RG 31/2/27 - Distributive Education Club
    - RG 31/2/28 - Epsilon Pi Tau (Industrial Arts/Vocational Education)
    - RG 31/2/29 - Food Science Club
    - RG 31/2/30 - Forensics Club
    - RG 31/2/31 - Forestry Club
    - RG 31/2/32 - French Club
    - RG 31/2/33 - Future Business Leaders of American (FBLA)
    - RG 31/2/34 - Geology Club
      See also RG 31/2.
    - RG 31/2/35 - History Club
    - RG 31/2/36 - Horticulture Club
      May include Horticulture Show
    - RG 31/2/37 - Home Economics Association
    - RG 31/2/38 - Industrial Arts Education Club
    - RG 31/2/39 - Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers
    - RG 31/2/40 - Mathematics Club
    - RG 31/2/41 - National Honor Society of Black Engineers
    - RG 31/2/42 - Philosophy Club
    - RG 31/2/43 - Pi Sigma Epsilon (Business) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      May include Virginia Tech Car Show
    - RG 31/2/44 - Poultry Science Club
    - RG 31/2/45 - Sigma Lambda Chi (Architecture)
    - RG 31/2/46 - Society of Architectural Engineers
    - RG 31/2/47 - Society of Automotive Engineers
    - RG 31/2/48 - Society of Physics Students
    - RG 31/2/49 - Soil Conservation Society
      May include Virginia Tech Soil Judging Team; Soil Science Society of America
    - RG 31/2/50 - Spanish Club
    - RG 31/2/51 - Student Art Association
    - RG 31/2/52 - Student Engineers Council
    - RG 31/2/53 - Student Dietetic Association
    - RG 31/2/54 - Virginia Education Association, Student Chapter
    - RG 31/2/55 - Virginia Society of Professional Engineers
    - RG 31/2/56 - Wildlife Society
    - RG 31/2/57 - Women in Communications, Inc. (WICI)
  - RG 31/3 - Dance Clubs [items also in Oversize Box 3]